בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, we start today the fourth פרק.
Perek. Today's דף Daf is למד אלף. Lamed Alef. We're at the
bottom of דף למד. Daf Lamed. And it is, what is it,
37 days of the עומר? Omer? 37. All right. משנה Mishnah here,
bottom of למד בית. Lamed-Bais.
לא היו כופתין. Lo Hayu Koftin. So we basically had that they
through lottery divided out all the different parts of the תמיד. Tamid.
And then we had the עבודה Avodah that they did actually before
the תמיד, Tamid, which wasn't the first people who won the lottery,
which was going in, opening the, well that wasn't the עבודה, Avodah,
but it was the first thing you did was you opened up
the gate of the היכל. Heichal. And you could only שחט shacht
the תמיד Tamid once the gate of the היכל Heichal was opened.
And then the two עבודות Avodot that they did inside the היכל,
Heichal, the cleaning of the ashes of the מנורה, Menorah, the cleaning
of the, well we did it out of order, the cleaning of
the ashes of the gold מזבח Mizbe'ach that they did for the
incense, and the cleaning of the ashes of the מנורה Menorah where
they started half of it. They cleaned it, they put it nearby,
they didn't complete the job. And now we finally get to the
actual שחיטה shechting of the תמיד, Tamid, of the morning sacrifice, which
is what this מסכת Masechet is named after. So let's take a
look. לא היו כופתין את הטלה. Lo Hayu Koftin et ha-taleh. Now
they actually interestingly go straight to the dismembering of it. I guess
there's not much to say about שחיטה. shechting. Meaning there is, or
there is a lot to say, it's the entire מסכת זבחים. Masechet
Zevachim. So we had a huge מסכת Masechet about the שחיטה shechting
and the זריקת הדם, zerekat hadam, so now we've jumped right over
that and gone straight to the dismembering. And if you remember, a
lot of the people what they got is in the lottery was
the right to bring the pieces of the קרבן Korban up to
the ramp of the altar. As Michael pointed out, it doesn't exactly
tell you who's doing the dismembering, but okay. So now, לא היו
כופתין את הטלה, Lo Hayu Koftin et ha-taleh, they would not bind
it, אלא מעקדין אותו, ella ma'akdin oto, they would be מעקדין ma'akdin
it. Now what does that mean? The general assumption means that כופת
kofet would mean you bind all four of its legs together, or
its two hind legs together and the two front legs together, sort
of as you imagine if somebody were carrying it, right? You know
that would be a convenient way because then you would get half
on each sort of side of your neck, you'd be able to
carry it on your shoulders.
No, that's what they would not do. They would not do the
hind legs together and the front legs together, or all four together,
but they would be מעקדין ma'akdin it. What is מעקדין? ma'akdin? It
means the front and the hind and the front and the hind.
Yes, that's what they would do. I was starting with what they
would not do.
Okay. Is this related to Isaac when he was bound?
Yes. So the גמרא Gemara exactly, so the גמרא Gemara is going
to pick up on that, this word עקד aked and עקידה, Akeidah,
and that this is the way יצחק Yitzchak was done, Isaac was
done. Correct. The רמב"ם Rambam has an interesting read of this which
means that they wouldn't bind it at all, but it's not clear
how we understand מעקדין ma'akdin and what that has to do with
עקידת יצחק. Akeidat Yitzchak. So the general assumption is they would not
do the front legs by themselves and the hind legs by themselves
or all four together, but they would combine a front and a
hind leg, a front and a hind leg. Of course by יצחק,
Yitzchak, right, did you imagine that you would do that to a
person? That would be very weird, wouldn't it?
Anyway, so that's also quite strange. We'll discuss it when we see
it in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So that's how they would bind
it. Now, מי שזכה באיברים אוחזין בו. mi she-zacho be-evarim ochzin bo.
Now the word,
now by the way, right, so that actually yes, we don't go
straight to dismembering, that is how they would sort of hold it
steady when they would שחט shacht it. Okay. So the normal assumption
is that they would bind the legs together in this way, front
and hind, front and hind, and put the neck through that metal
circle that we discussed yesterday and therefore שחט, shacht, and that would
hold it steady. The רמב"ם Rambam understands as I said that they
did not actually bind it with a rope at all, but
they put the legs, again I have to double check the רמב"ם
Rambam exactly how he said it, but that they do the legs
into that metal circle, into that
metal ring, ring, into that metal ring, so that they wouldn't be
bound but they would put the legs through that ring. Anyway, but
so they would bind it up in this way in order to
make it easier to שחט shacht and they would have it in
the metal ring. Now then they would שחט shacht it and be
זורק הדם. zorek hadam. Now we get to the dismembering. מי שזכה
באיברים אוחזין בו. mi she-zacho be-evarim ochzin bo. The people that had
the right to,
the people that had, I'm sorry I keep on jumping ahead too
quickly. We haven't שחט shachted it yet. The people that are going
to be the ones that are going to bring the limbs up
to the altar hold onto it. They participate. And there's a lot
of those people, they're like ten of those people. I can't imagine
that you need ten people for one little sheep, but okay. Various
ones of them are involved in holding it steady when they שחט
shacht it. וכך היה עקידתו. ve-khakh hayah akedat-o. And here's how it
would be bound and how it would be standing when they שחט
shachted it. ראשו לדרום. rosho la-darom. It would be facing south. ופניו
למערב. u-panav le-ma'arav. And its head would be to the south and
its face would be to the west. והשוחט עומד במזרח ופניו למערב.
ve-ha-shochet omed ba-mizrach u-panav la-ma'arav. And the one who שחט shachted it
would be to the east and his face would be to the
west. So what that would mean would be the following. If you
assume that this is here your orientation of the מקדש, Mikdash, right?
It's rectangular. Here's your altar. Okay. Here's the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim
over here. Okay. Now this is צפון, north, this is מזרח. east.
Okay. It opens in the מזרח, east, it goes to the מערב.
west. So you are supposed to שחט shacht it to the צפון
north of the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So you're here. Okay, now, its rear
is toward that way, it's towards the north because if it has
to not be disrespectful and certainly if it drops dung, you don't
want it dropping dung in front of the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So its
rear is that way, so its head, its oriented north-south.
This is also to the north of the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, but its
rear is to the north, away, and its head is to the
south. So that's why it
says ראשו
לדרום. rosho ledarom. Now, although it would be oriented lengthwise north-south with
the head in the north and the whole thing to the south
of the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, you would have its face pointing to the
west because you want it to face the, you know, the קודש
Kodesh and the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, the היכל. Heichal. And you
would be standing on the other side, you would be behind it,
so your rear would not be to the היכל. Heichal. So you
would be facing the היכל, Heichal, its face would be facing the
היכל, Heichal, you would be towards its east, it would be facing
towards the west, you'd stand here and you would שחט shecht it.
Okay, so do you see that? It says ראשו לדרום, rosho ledarom,
its head is south, פניו למערב panav lama'arav facing west, השוחט עומד
במזרח hashocheit omeid bamizrach you stand to the east ופניו למערב upanav
lama'arav and you're also facing west. Okay, so is that clear?
We'll just make another picture here.
Here's
the בית, Beis, this is north, okay,
so it says you have to שחט shecht קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodoshim
in the north. So here's going to be your cow or your
sheep. Okay, you like that now? So it's facing south so that
its rear is not away from the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Here's the היכל.
Heichal.
Okay, its head is oriented towards the west facing
the היכל Heichal and you are standing in the east also oriented
towards the west so your rear is not towards the היכל Heichal
either. Okay, and you שחט shecht it. All right,
so okay. שחרית היה נשחט על קרן צפונית מערבית. Shacharit hayah nishchat
al keren tzevonit ma'aravit. In the morning one was שחט shechted in
the northwest corner על טבעת שנייה, al taba'at shniyah, the second ring.
I'll explain this in a minute. שבבין הערביים, Shebe'ein ha'arbayim, the afternoon
one היה נשחט על קרן מזרחית צפונית hayah nishchat al keren mizrachit
tzevonit the I'm sorry did I say that? Yeah, the northeast one
על טבעת שנייה, al taba'at shniyah, the second ring. Now, what does
that mean?
It means that here they had all of the rings
that
they used to hang the heads of the קרבנות korbanot in according
to the רמב"ם Rambam the legs and the feet, right?
And they had twenty-four of them. There were because there were twenty-four
משמרות. mishmarot. Each one had a ring designated for them
and בלגה Bilgah was filled in.
Exactly. Now, they were six by four. Now, so each one, each
משמר mishmar had a designated one. But for the תמיד, tamid, they
always used the same ring. So the morning one was which direction
was the morning one?
צפונית מערבית.
Tzevonit ma'aravit. Northwest. Was this one. And you would have thought the
northwesternmost, but according to other sources, it's one removed. And the afternoon
one was northeast. This one. Second. Why second? Right. Why? So, well
the second, I'll tell you the second in a minute. The reason
here is that it's because first of all it's supposed to be
as close to the מזבח Mizbe'ach as possible. So that's why we've
got it, that's why we've got it in the I'm sorry.
Northeast should be on the upper right. That's northwest.
That's no oh I'm sorry.
I did south I did I did south.
If you're doing northwest, that's one furthest from the מזבח Mizbe'ach
actually
and the north northeast and northwest. Right. Okay. So, okay, let me
double check as to why the north. The east and the west
is because in the morning you've got the rising sun here. Okay,
and we learned that it's supposed to be opposite the rising sun,
so the morning one is here, which is in the west opposite
the rising sun. The afternoon one is here, which is in the
east opposite the rising sun opposite the setting sun. Okay, that's why
the morning one is in the west, afternoon one is in the
east. It's opposite where the sun is. Is that clear?
Yeah, I understand that. You could you could just turn yours around
a little. Okay.
Okay, here, right? It's where the opposite where the sun is. Now,
the reason it's the second is apparently hold on
maybe these two.
I mean you
mean Let me just let me just recheck the מפרשים meforshim and
make sure I'm saying this right. One minute.
One minute.
על טבעת שנייה, Al taba'at shniyah,
it says second.
Okay,
got it.
Okay, fine. So, apparently, here's the idea. Okay, this was here was
the wall of the of the Of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
right?
There are two pointers that were found here. The reason it's as
north as possible, one, one remove, is because it says you שחט
shechet it at the north. Okay. Right. You try to do as
north as possible to emphasize the idea of north. Why is the
morning one in the west? Because we learned that it says you
שחט shecht it, you know, it says שנים ליום, shnayim layom, you
know, and the idea of יום yom means the sun, that it's
opposite the sun. So if you have the rising sun in the
east, so if it sort of wants to most be getting the
sun, as it were, then the morning it would be in the
west. And if the setting sun's in the west, you want to
most be getting the sun, it would be in the east. Why
is it one remove? It's one remove because of the shadow cast
by the north wall. So if it was in this, you know,
if it were here, it would not really be getting the sun.
You want to be over here, so it's getting the sun. So
it's north, so it gets the sun. It's one remove, so it's
away from the shadow, and it's east and west so that it
is opposite the rising and setting sun.
But I would have thought that the reason why you do it
kind of opposite is because, you know, if it rises in the
east, you want to specifically in the morning do it in the
west, showing that you're not doing it towards the sun.
I hear you. Right, I understand. We will look because you know,
because it's like not about sun worship and all of that. All
right, we'll see the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara learns a פסוק
pasuk that says it's supposed to be opposite the sun. All right,
anyways, so that's basically the idea. North to emphasize north, opposite the
sun, one remove so it's out of the shadow. Okay.
Now, שחט השוחט, shachat hashocheit, so you see I ran ahead, we
actually didn't do the שחיטה shechita yet. We have it bound, we
have it in its right ring, and now we're going to שחט
shecht it. וקיבל המקבל, vekibel hamikabel, and the one who caught the
blood, caught the blood. בא לו לקרן מזרחית צפונית, ba lo lekeren
mizrachit tzevonit, he came to the northeastern corner. ונותן ונותן מזרחה צפונה,
venotein venotein mizracha tzevona,
and he puts the blood, he throws the blood on the northeastern
corner of the מזבח. mizbeach. מערבית דרומית, maaravit deromit, he comes to
the southwestern corner. ונותן מערבה דרומה, venotein maarava deroma, and he puts
the blood on the southwestern corner. So they would sprinkle the blood
of all
basically חטאת chatas except for חטאת chattas and one or two exceptions
on diagonal corners.
So it says מזרחית צפונית, mizrachit tzevonit, right? So first he would
come here and he'd sprinkle the blood here, and then he would,
what's, sprinkle the blood that way, מזרחה צפונה. mizracha tzevona. And then,
and then southwest. Okay, so he would שחט shecht here, walk over
here, throw the blood there, walk around, throw the blood there, and
that's where the blood would be thrown. Okay, and that would be
the זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam.
Same, same כהן kohen שחטס shechts and throws?
No, one כהן kohen שחטס, shechts, another one catches the blood and
moves it and takes it to the מזבח mizbeach and throws it.
Those are two separate things. All right, so that would be the
זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam.
Okay, שירי הדם, shearei hadam, the remainder of the blood היה שופך
אל יסוד דרומי haya shofech al yesod dromi would be spilled out
on the southern bank.
Okay, so here we finish over here, and he'd spill out the
blood here on the southern bank.
All right, fine.
Very good. Now, the thing you have to know is that the
actual יסוד yesod itself was, was, it was a little strange. The
יסוד yesod itself really did not go all the way around the
מזבח. mizbeach. The יסוד yesod itself only went like this. That's what
the יסוד yesod looked like. Okay, so you have to do the
זריקת הדם zerikas hadam opposite the יסוד. yesod. So since this northwest
corner did not have a יסוד, yesod, you could not do it
opposite corners, which is why you do it at southwest and northeast,
because those are the only two available opposite corners. And when you
spilled it out at the southern יסוד, yesod, you really could only
spill it out right here. You only had a little bit of
a corner here at the southern יסוד. yesod. This part did not
have a יסוד. yesod.
Why opposite doesn't mean those two, you know, straight lines, it has
to be diagonal?
No, the only available diagonal corner. Why have to be diagonal, though?
Because it has to be סביב. saviv. It has to be, by
doing it diagonally, I should spell that out, by doing it diagonally
you've got it on all four walls. Okay, you see?
If
you do these two, you've got those two walls and those two,
those two walls, you have to get it all around.
All right, I understand.
But you could do it on three corners and then you'd get...
That's the מסורה. masorah. לא היה שובר בו lo haya shover bo
atop of ל"א ע"א. lamed-aleph amud-aleph. Now we did the זריקת הדם,
zerikas hadam, שחיטה shechita and זריקה. zerika. Now we are getting to
the, I guess the reason I spoke, I emphasized the dismembering is
that's most of what this פרק perek is about. But yes, first
we have how you bound it, where you put it in the
ring, how you שחט shecht it, זריקת הדם, zerikas hadam, and now
we get to the dismembering. לא היה שובר בו lo haya shover
bo את הרגל. es haregel. They would not break the, the leg.
Apparently, sometimes when you would suspend a sheep or a cow in
order to flay it and dismember it, a classic thing would be
done would be somehow be through the breaking of a leg would
make it more convenient I guess to hang it. But they would
not do it this way. אלא נוקבו מתוך ארכובו. ella nokvo mitoch
arkuvo. But rather you would make a hole in it by its
heel, I believe is the ארכובו. arkuvo. Is the ארכובו arkuvo the
heel? Hold on.
ארכובו... arkuvo... Okay. Yes, no, oh wow, you got a lot of
pictures there. Okay. Anyway. Okay. So they would make a- so they
would make some type of a hole in its- in its lower
leg. וטלה בו, vetala bo, and they would suspend it.
Is it- here the ארכובו, arkuvo, excuse me, is the knee. The
knee.
Okay.
That's interesting because we'll get to the knee a little bit later.
Okay fine. So anyway they would make some type of a- they
would make some type of a hole in its knee, some area
of the lower leg. Actually cows have two knees, you know, two
sort of joints, not sure about sheep. Anyway they would suspend it-
they would suspend it through that. Now, וטלה בו, vetala bo, and
they would suspend it through that. היה מפשיט ויורד, haya mafshit veyored,
now they would- they would be flaying it and going down. And
you have to understand it's being suspended by its- its hind legs
are on the top, so going down means going towards the head.
Okay, it's being suspended by its legs. היה מפשיט ויורד עד שמגיע
לחזה, haya mafshit veyored ad shemagia lachaze,
until he came to the chest. So it's being flayed till the
chest area. הגיע לחזה, higia lachaze, comes to the chest area, חתך
את הראש, chatach et harosh, so the head now was cut off.
They would not flay the head. They would do the head with
its- with its skin on it.
So did they cut the head off now?
Yes, now, when they got to the chest. It's now flayed up
to the chest, okay, so basically pretty much all of the stuff-
all the skin has been removed except for like the head area,
maybe like the top shoulders. So they would cut off the head,
ונתנו למי שזכה בה, venasno lemi shezacha bah,
and they'd give the head to the one who- who got the
head. The first כהן kohen after the one- after the זורק zorek
and whatever, after, you know, the first one who gets the- sections
gets the head. חתך את הכרעיים, chatach et hakraayim, now they cut
off the כרעיים kraayim
which is also like the lower legs, ונתנו למי שזכה בהן, venasno
lemi shezacha bahen, and gave it to the one who merited them.
One minute, 10 is...
Okay, they cut off the lower legs and they gave it to
the one that merited them. Now, this apparently again, by cows- cows
have two- two- has two joints in their legs. They have one
that is sort of- I guess we do too, you know, we
have like a knee and we have an ankle, but their ankle
sort of thing is a little bit higher. Anyway, apparently this means
that they would cut it off like right at the- sort of
joint right near the feet. So essentially you're cutting off the feet
here, not the primary leg, but you're cutting off the feet and
they gave that to the one who merited them. Now, מרק את
ההפשט, mirak et hahefshet, and now- now- it doesn't say interestingly in
who gets the various pieces who got the feet, but be that
as it may. מרק את ההפשט, mirak et hahefshet, and they finished
the complete
flaying, וקרע את הלב, vekara et halev, and they tore the heart
והוציא את דמו, vehotzi et damo, and got its blood out. Now
this is a very strange line to say that right now they
tore the heart- they ripped up the heart and got out its
blood. Why is it a strange line? Who's been paying attention? Why
where are they up to right now in- in dismembering this animal?
The only thing they've cut, they've removed the skin is they've cut
off the feet, right? So then they said and after they cut
off the feet and finished flaying it, they tore open the heart
and took out its blood. Is there a problem here? How do
you get to the heart? The heart is still in the chest
cavity. You haven't opened up the chest cavity. Okay, so there's a
whole question what this means. Does it mean that they made a
particular incision in order to remove the heart? Does it- is this
really out of place or it really means when they're going to
get to the heart they're going to remove the blood and what's
this line doing here? So there's a whole question what this line
is doing here to say that they tore open the heart and
removed its blood. Simple is to say that it means when they
got to it that's what they would do. Of course why it's
being mentioned here is not clear. Anyway, moving back, חתך את הידיים
chatach et hayadayim ונתנו למי שזכה בהן. venasno lemi shezacha bahen.
Then they went ahead and they cut off the hands
and they gave them to the- to the one that inherited- to
inherit- the one that- that won them sort of in the lottery.
Hold on.
One minute. Okay.
Yeah, now, again, the little question here about the ידיים, yadayim, I'm
just trying to get this again, how the ידיים yadayim is different
than the כרעיים kraayim before.
The ידיים yadayim are presumably the front hands of the animal. Right,
right. Okay, so those are the front hands of the animal. So
what you've got is-
by the way based on the picture in the Artscroll, the two
regions that you're using are those- are those two- is-
is
this- it's here.
But what he said was well look- he said this whole eastern-
he said over here if you look, this whole eastern wall, right,
by the שחר shachar you want to- you want to get it
over here so that you don't have a shadow.
Yeah,
I understand the reason, but the משנה mishna says מזרחית צפונית.
mizrachit tzephonit. צפונית Tzephonit means north- north...
relative to the one on the... I think you're right. I think
you're right. That's why I originally drew this, this one. But when
it says it was north, it does not mean northernmost. It means
northern relative to the outer outer row. Look, I understand the logic,
I just don't get why it would specifically say north. Anyway, getting
to your hanging calves here. Let's deal with your hanging calves. It's
actually a sheep. Okay, there's your hanging sheep. Okay, so I guess
the first thing here would be the tangle.
Anyway, we'll give it some wool maybe.
Okay, I guess the tail would be coming out here. Give it
some
wool anyway. Okay, so when you started, it says that you cut
off the קרעיים, Krayim, which are the lower feet area. Now it
says you've done the הפשט Hafshet on it so far. Okay, so
you've done the הפשט, Hafshet, you pulled off the skin, you cut
off the head.
And now that you cut off the head, it says what did
you do next after cutting off the head and giving that to
the one
that gets it, well the heart, but we're going to skip exactly
what that means by the heart. Then it says you finished flaying,
and then it says חתך את הידיים. Chatach et Hayadayim. Now you've
got the הידיים Hayadayim which are the front hands. Okay, and the
person who gets the הידיים Hayadayim gets those because a different person
gets the front hands, gets the back. So now we've got the
front hands. Now, okay, עלה לרגל הימנית, Ala l'regel hayemanit, חתכה ונתנה
למי שזכה בה. Chatacha unetana l'mi shezacha bah.
Then you went to the right leg,
right sort of relative to the בהמה Behema here, which is this
one. So now it's actually being represented by the left leg.
And you took off and you cut off the right leg. The
right leg goes and you've also cut off the head now. The
right leg and the head go together, these go to person number
one. Okay, so now you've cut off the right leg. Who gets
the hands by the way? What did the previous משנה Mishnah say
about who gets the hands?
שתי ידיים Shtei yadayim goes to the next person.
Okay, so now you see what you've done here, right, this is
the order here, the א, Aleph, ב Beis of the people. The
order you've done it is one, then you did this, then you
did that. Okay, now you've cut off the right leg.
So now we've got person number one and person number two's portion.
Now, חתך את הידיים ונתנן למי שזכה בהן, עלה לרגל הימנית וחתכה
ונתנה למי שזכה בה. Chatach et hayadayim unetanan l'mi shezacha bahen, ala
l'regel hayemanit vechatacha unetana l'mi shezacha bah. So now you cut off
the right leg and you gave it to the כהן Kohen that's
going to bring that up, the first כהן Kohen א. Aleph. Now,
וביצים עמה, Ubeitzim ima,
together with the right leg, you had the two testicles. Those went
with the right leg. קרעו ונמצא כולו גלוי לפניו. Kerao venimtza kulo
galui lefanav.
Then you cut it down lengthwise and you opened it up. Okay,
נטל את הפדר ונתנו על בית שחיטת הראש מלמעלה. Natal et hapeder
unetano al beis shechitas harosh milmala.
So you cut it open, okay, now he's cut it open, and
he took out the fat and what they did is they used
the fat, they put that together with the head and they put
it right around the place where the head was severed, the severing
mark, the cut mark of the head because that was a nice
way, that sort of covered it up, it was all bloody and
whatever, so you surrounded it with fat. Okay, so now we've got
some fat here going together with the head. All right, so that's
what we've done next.
Now, נטל את הקרביים. Natal et hakirvayim.
Now you took all of the inner organs, ונתנם למי שזכה בהן
להדיחן, Unetanam l'mi shezacha bahen l'hadichan, and you gave them to the
person who's going to get the inner organs to rinse them out.
Which person was he in the lottery? Let's take a look back.
You had הראש והרגל, Harosh veharegel, של שמאל, Shel smol, החזה והגרה,
Hechaze vehagera, ושתי דפנות, Ushtei defanos, הקרביים Hakirvayim was the last guy,
ו. Vav.
Okay,
so now you took out the inner organs, here we'll draw what
does this look like, a small intestine and your stomach or whatever.
Anyway, you gave them to person number ו, Vav, and he is
here putting them on the table and he is rinsing them out.
Okay, so that's what he did next.
Now you've got the inner organs.
Okay, what my understanding is, one
minute, להדיחן והכרס, L'hadichan vehakeres,
and also right, so the inner organs and the stomach, מדיחין אותו
בבית המדיחין, Madichin oso beveis hamadichin,
and you rinse it out in the place of rinsing which was
those tables we mentioned
before, the little pillars were for שחיטה Shechitah and the tables were
for rinsing. ומדיחין אותה כל צרכה, Umadichin osa kol tzorka, and you
rinse it out all as required to get out all of the
obviously the fecal matter and so on. והקרביים
מדיחין אותם שלוש פעמים, Vehakirvayim madichin osam shalosh peamim, the stomach you
do as much as you need, what I don't know if that
means more or less than the intestines, and the intestines you do
three times, במיעוטן Bemiutan minimally three times,
על שולחנות שיש Al shulchanos shayish on those marble tables, שבין העמודים
Shebein haamudim that are between the pillars.
Now, because here's where you would שחט, Shacht, okay, here you would
have pillars, and those pillars... would be for I mean this thing
here this
הבלטה hablatta over here you know this plating would be done on
the pillars. Okay here's where you're doing your flaying. Okay on these
pillars okay that's where it would be done. You שחט shacht over
here you take it to the pillars and next to the pillars
were tables that were rinsing tables. Okay so your flaying is here,
anything that you need to get some rinse you move them over
to the tables
and you rinse out the intestines on the tables.
Yes Michael.
So what I'm trying to understand is when he was when he
was doing this skinning of the animal right so he did top
to bottom right? Yep. And then he went out this way right?
Yeah. So did he actually skin the area of the עכוז? akuz?
So that's what it sounds like yeah. But how? I mean like
it says until you go to the חזה. chazeh. So the חזה
chazeh is like right here isn't it? What?
Yeah but then it says he finished. No first he cut off
the head וחתך את הראש vechatach es harosh then and then חתך
את הכרעיים. chatach es hakaraim.
Right.
The כרעיים karaim were basically the joints right near the feet. Those
were not what we call the ידים yadayim and the רגלים. raglayim.
Those were just the very bottom.
Right so that part like that part wasn't flayed.
That part wasn't flayed okay fine
okay so why is that?
I don't know I assume it's too difficult to flay that part.
Okay try ever try removing the skin from like a wing of
a chicken as opposed to from like the breast area? A certain
section it's so bony and whatever it's hard to remove. Okay moving
on. נטל את הסכין והפריש את הריאה מן הכבד ואצבע הכבד מן
הכבד. natal es hasakin vehiprish es harayah min hakaved veetzba hakaved min
hakaved.
So he used a knife and what he did was he didn't
cut it out but he separated he cut in order to separate
like at the joining part the lung from the liver from the
lobe of the liver. What's the lobe of the liver by the
way? What do we call that? What organ is that? It's some
organ. Anyway from the lobe of the liver. ולא היה מזיזה ממקומה.
velo hayah mezizah mimekoma. Now he did not actually remove the lobe
of the liver from where it was because each one of these
the lung the liver the lobe of the liver which are basically
attached to one another each one of them is going to go
with a different section of the animal. So he separated them but
he did not remove them. Now נוקב את החזה ונתנה למי שזכה
בה. noikev es hachazeh unesanah lemi shezachah bah.
So he made a hole in the chest and he gave it
to the person who inherited it's funny to who inherited who merited
it. It's funny the phrase a hole in the chest but okay.
But it means that he cut out the chest and he gave
it to the person who got it. עלה לדופן הימנית. alah ledofen
hayemanis. And then he's going to come to the right flank.
So basically here he is okay he also separated out some he
opened it up now okay because it said he opened it up.
Now he took the chest area okay and he gave the chest
to
the person who gets the chest. Who gets the chest? What did
the previous משנה mishnah say which one? I'm doing a b and
c. So you have the שתי ידים shtei yadayim who comes after
the שתי ידים? shtei yadayim?
העוקץ והרגל haoketz veharegel is c. שמאל החזה והגרה smol hachazeh vehagerah
that's d.
Okay so d now got the chest.
Okay now what he's going to do is he's going to
the chest was just this
area this whole length of the animal which was like the major
part I mean again we're talking about a sheep not a cow
but you have the flanks. Now we're moving to the flanks.
Why is the rinsing though? Aren't they all done in the בית
המטבחיים? beis hamitbachayim? Why are some of them down on these tables?
This table is the בית המטבחיים. beis hamitbachayim. That is the בית
המטבחיים. beis hamitbachayim. Look at your picture.
No right no but then the next one is הקרביים הדיחן שלוש
פעמים על שולחנות השיש שבין העמודים hakirvayim hedichan shalosh peamim al shulchanos
hashayish shebein haamudim right?
So
I don't think it's true it's separating it but I don't understand
I
it's all referring to the same things that's the way I understand
it. You're right it's a little funny the way it says החזה
hachazeh and then המדיח. hamadiach.
But isn't this לשכת המדיחין? lishkas hamadichin? They didn't do it in
the לשכת המדיחין? lishkas hamadichin? The בית המדיחין beis hamadichin what? Didn't
they do it in
what's לשכת המדיחין lishkas hamadichin then?
I don't know I understood it maybe you're right I understood it
that the בית המטבחיים beis hamitbachayim was going on everything. That that
the קרביים kirvayim and the כרס keres were בית המטבחיים. beis hamitbachayim.
You understand
that בית המטבחיים beis hamitbachayim was the לשכה?
lishkah? בית המדיחין? beis hamadichin? המדיחין? hamadichin?
I mean that's what I would have
thought
it is. The other thing is what this note says actually the
way they translate this the כרס keres the stomach they rinsed it
in the rinsing chamber away from the temple courtyard. So the chamber
would be the לשכה. lishkah. That makes sense.
Wait
one minute I'm sorry you're correct the מפרש mefaresh says the same
thing. One minute. Okay
yeah my okay I stand corrected. Right the מפרש mefaresh says the
same thing. So going back to that it did separate the the
stomach from the intestines and the stomach it said בבית המדיחין beveis
hamadichin and the intestines it said on the tables. And you're right
the מפרש mefaresh says that because the stomach had more fecal matter
and waste matter they did it in a separate room.
Why didn't they do everything in a separate room?
Why do some of them over there? I don't know. I mean,
no, because you're here, you're not here, you're here.
You're taking it out, aren't you? What?
I mean, if you're just taking it out. I know, but it's
like, especially if it's not a big deal, you want to just
process it as quickly right where you are. Okay, so I stand
corrected on that point.
So yes, so according to the מפרשים, meforshim, מפרשים meforshim is right,
it did use a separate phrase.
That they are over here with something called the rinse room, the
בית המדיחין. beit hamidichin. And so that, so they would take the
stomach, they would actually take the stomach here, the intestines they would
do right over here near where they was. But the stomach because
it particularly,
you know, had particularly a lot of waste and fecal matter they
would do it separately. But where where is that located?
It's located at
the other end of the מזבח mizbeach at the other end of
the מזבח.
mizbeach.
So they would take it all the way over there.
Oh.
All right, so you are correct. It does separate the two. So
you're right, I conflated them. Thank you. Okay.
So what do we have?
Shechted over
here, shechted over here, brought over here to the tables to be
flayed, was flayed, separated out as we've seen, the stomach brought over
to this room to be cleaned, the other intestines put on the
table to be cleaned, and now we are dismembering it. And now
we've taken out
we've taken the head and the and the head and the right
rear, rightmost leg, we've taken the two
arms, and now we've taken out the intestines as we said, and
now we've taken out the chest. Okay, and now we go on
back to the משנה. mishna.
Where are we?
Okay. עלה לדופן הימנית, ala ladofen hayemanit,
you came to the right flank. היה חותך ויורד עד השדרה, haya
choteich veyoreid ad hashidra, you would cut it until you got to
the spinal cord in the back and you'd keep on cutting down,
so you'd be cutting basically from the feet towards the head. ולא
היה נוגע בשדרה, velo haya nogeia bashidra, you wouldn't actually cut the
spinal cord, get into the spinal cord. עד שמגיע לבין שתי צלעות,
ad shemagia levein shetei tzlaot, until you got to the two little
ribs, right? There's two little ribs at the bottom and at the
top of the spinal cord. דקות, dakot, small, thin ones. וחתכה ונתנה
למי שזכה בה, vechatacha unetana lemi shezacha bah, so you gave that
flank to the one who won it in the lottery. והכבד תלויה
בה ve-hakaveid tluya bah with the liver attached to it. Basically what
you did now was you cut out this flank, okay,
up to the spinal cord and not and you went all the
way down towards the head, but you know you left the two
little ribs here and we're going to find out there's two little
ribs up there, and you gave that right flank with the liver
to the one who inherited it. Who gets the flank? Does it
say?
שתי דפנות. shetei defanot. So that's the next guy.
שתי דפנות. shetei defanot. Right, that would be in
our little thing that would be number E.
So E is going to get the two flanks, he's got one
of the flanks now. Okay. Okay.
Where are we? Okay. Now, והכבד תלויה בה. ve-hakaveid tluya bah. בא
לו לגירה. ba lo lagera. Now you came to the actual like
to the throat area. הניח בה שתי צלעות מכאן ושתי צלעות מכאן.
hiniach bah shetei tzlaot mikan ushetei tzlaot mikan. You didn't go into
the two, you know, the two little ribs that we said were
at the top and at the bottom.
I'm sorry, you're now at the neck, the neck doesn't have any
ribs.
Well, the top of the spinal cord
here, right, this is the spinal cord, so that's the whole point,
don't cut into the two ribs.
Okay. You go, you leave those two ribs, שתי צלעות. shetei tzlaot.
And what do you do? Basically they're decapitated, so it
just has like a little bit of neck left.
Right, exactly. Okay.
One minute, one second.
One minute.
Okay, anyway, so you cut out that space, the space of the
throat area. One minute, where am I? בא לו לגירה, הניח בה
שתי צלעות מכאן ושתי צלעות מכאן, ba lo lagera, hiniach bah shetei
tzlaot mikan ushetei tzlaot mikan, וחתכה ונתנה למי שזכה בה. vechatacha unetana
lemi shezacha bah.
So you cut out the throat area. הקנה והלב והריאה תלויים בה.
hakaneh vehalev veharei’ah tluyim bah. And there you have the trachea, the
heart, and the lungs.
Okay, so who got that area, the גירה? gera? So the גירה
gera went together with the, if you take a look, went together
with the chest, right? החזה והגירה. hachazeh vehagera.
So it went together with the chest. So therefore the guy here
who got the chest, D, now essentially what you're doing is you're
cutting out this section, which is the throat area with the heart
and the lungs and so on.
Didn't you say something earlier about the heart?
Yeah, so that was out of place. Whenever you got to the
heart, you're going to get the blood out of the heart. So
you're going to open it up and get the blood.
But we didn't have
to cut away the heart. Right, correct.
So anyway, first you gave him the chest area from the animal,
now you gave him the throat with all of the organs hanging
from it.
All right,
now there we are. All right, so you gave it to that
person.
בא לו לדופן
השמאלית.
Ba lo ledofen
hasmalit. Now you came to the left flank. הניח בה שתי צלעות
דקות מלמעלה ושתי צלעות דקות מלמטה, Hiniach bah shtei tzalot dakot milmalah
ushtei tzalot dakot milmatah, and you didn't go into the two little
ribs on the top and the bottom, right? Which is the very,
which is the very tail area of the animal and the very
sort of top of the neck area of the animal. וכך היה
מניח בחברתה, Vekach hayah maniach bechavertah, and you would also leave on
the other side, right as we said before, when you cut away
the right flank, you would not go to the very tip of
the top and the very tip of the bottom where those two
ribs are on each side. נמצא מניח שתיים שתיים מלמעלה שתיים שתיים
מלמטה. Nimtza maniach shtayim shtayim milmalah shtayim shtayim milmatah. So there were
two ribs on the top and two ribs on the bottom that
you left, the little ones. חתכה ונתנה למי שזכה בה. Chatachah unetanah
lemi shezachah bah. והשדרה עמה. Vehashidra imah. You cut it together with
the spinal cord because you left the spinal cord over from the
other one, from the right flank, and you gave it to the
person who won it. והטחול תלוי בה. Vehatachol talui bah. And the
spleen was attached to it. והיא היתה גדולה. Vehi hayetah gedolah. This
was bigger because it had the spinal cord attached to it, so
obviously it's going to be the bigger half because it's coming with
the spinal cord. אלא שהימין קורין גדולה. Ela shehayamin korin gedolah. You
call the right one the big one. שהכבד תלויה בה. Shehakaved teluyah
bah. Because the right one has the liver, and in ancient times
the liver was considered to be like the seat of intelligence. So
since the liver came with the right one, that was considered the
big, the important one.
Okay, so now basically what have you done? Now you cut away
the rest of the flank here with the spinal cord, right?
And that also goes to the, goes to the next guy. So
he's getting this piece. You've already done the chest area, and the
throat, you've done the hands, you've done the feet. You've done pretty
much everything except for, we're going to see, except for the tail
area, which is what we're coming to next.
Okay. בא לו לעוקץ. Ba lo le'oketz. You came to the tail.
חתכו. Chatacho. You cut it away. ונתנו למי שזכה בו. Unetano lemi
shezachah bo. And you gave it to the one who won it.
והאליה ואצבע הכבד. Veha'alyah ve'etzba hakaved. Now the fat tail because it's
a sheep and the lobe of the liver. ושתי כליות עמו. Ushtei
klayot imo. And the two kidneys.
Oh, actually, I said before, I think I misspoke. I said before
that it was the liver was the seat, but it's actually the
kidneys that are the seat of the intelligence. So I'm not sure
why they're saying that why they gave so much weight to the
liver that they called it big. Well, the liver is huge, right?
I mean, the liver is a very, very large part of the
animal. Hold on a second, let me see if המפרש Hamefaresh says
here.
Yeah, המפרש Hamefaresh just says because the liver was an extra thing.
Okay, but I take it back. I meant the kidneys actually are
considered the seat of the intelligence basically.
So the lobe of the liver is different from the liver?
Yeah, it's, yes. Okay, so anyway, ושתי כליות עמו. Ushtei klayot imo.
So anyway, so the left flank was the bigger one, the right
flank had the liver, and therefore they called it the big one
because the liver was a big extra thing. Now you're at the
tail. The tail had the lobe of the liver and the two
kidneys. נטל את הרגל השמאלית. Natal et haregel hasmalit. You took the
left leg. חתכה ונתנה למי שזכה בה. Chatachah unetanah lemi shezachah bah.
And you gave it to the one who got it. נמצאו כולן
עומדים בשורה. Nimtze'u kulan omdim beshurah. Now obviously the last thing you're
going
to do is the left leg because it hangs by the left
leg. So anyway, so now finally you cut this part, the C,
right, which is the tail, which also has the kidneys, etc. And
then when you're finally done, you cut off the leg here, the
C, and now everybody
has their part and the whole thing is dismembered. ושלום על ישראל.
Veshalom al Yisrael. Everybody has their part and their person. Now, yeah.
So basically if you're, you made a hole in that knee, right?
Yeah, and that's where, so basically when it says when you did
the קרעיים. Krayim. That was like one of the things you did
in the very, very beginning.
You did not include the left one. Or it did. I keep
on telling you that the קרעיים Krayim are just the areas of
like the foot area, okay? So you could still suspend it by
its knee. But yes, now you finally have to take it off
the hanging and the little part that it's hanging by, so that
also goes to the C guy, and he is the one that
brings that. That's part of the left leg. Yeah.
Is there any significance given to this order?
No, other than that this was the most convenient way of doing
it, it seems to be. Yeah, המפרש Hamefaresh says something about that.
He says like, he says, here let me see if I can
find the line. He says,
he
says like, wait a minute,
yeah, at one point he says, וכל הסדר הזה אין שום פיסוק
כי
אם סברא. Vechol haseder hazeh ein shum
pissuk ki
im sevara. פסוק? Pasuk? אלא כי אם סברא. Ela ki im sevara.
לפי מה שנכון לעשות עושים. Lefi mah shenachon la'asot osim.
Like
let's do it whatever way makes the most convenient logical sense, you
know? There's not like there's a ritual way in doing it, but
this was the most efficient, this was the way they had it
figured out. Okay, so now we go on. נטל את הרגל השמאלית
וחתכה. Natal et haregel hasmalit vechatachah. נמצאו כולם עומדים בשורה. Nimtze'u kulam
omdim beshurah.
Everybody is standing in a line because they gave each piece to
the appropriate person as they finished processing it. They didn't necessarily. to
all of your stuff at once as we saw; sometimes they came
together, sometimes they were separate, but as they finished they gave it,
and everybody is standing in a line.
Me, I thought I got his piece ten minutes ago, just sitting
there.
Exactly. אוי נעבעך. Oy nebach. Yes, yes, וכולם בידם, vekulam beyadam, they're
all holding onto the various
limbs. הראשון בראש וברגל, Harishon berosh uveragel, A, there the first one
gets the head and the foot. הראש בימינו וחוטמו כלפי זרועו, Harosh
bimino vechotmo klapei zero'o, he had the head in his right hand,
that's the most important, the nose is facing not like pointing out,
you know, but sort of pointed on, you know, the head's oriented
so the nose is facing against his arm, so it's like he
doesn't feel appropriate to have a nose pointing up.
וקרניו בין אצבעותיו, Vekarnav bein etzbe'otav, holding the horns between his fingers,
so just basically so he could grasp it well for stability. ובית
שחיטתו מלמעלה, Uveit shechitato milma'alah,
and the place where it was shechted, the severing place was pointed
up. והפדר נתונה עליהם, Veha-peder netunah aleihem, and the fat on them,
and the fat on it as we said before is a nice
way of that was deemed very aesthetically nice and covered up the
actual place of the severing, and the fat was seen as the
best part so you have the head with the fat and those
two things as the best part. So basically the way it would
be is if you had a head pointed
down... No, okay. So if you hold the nose this way and
the horns this way and it's a little bit oriented like this,
then the shechitah place is up here and you put the fat
over there.
And even although also if you have it up, wouldn't it drip
down?
I guess. Okay. Okay. הרגל של ימין בשמאלו, Haregel shel yamin bismolo,
and the left hand carried the right, the right leg. And the
head and the leg, yes, and the right, not the, yeah, and
the rear leg, the rear right leg. ובית העור מבחוץ, Uveit ha'or
mibachutz, and the place of their skin is on the outside, meaning
it was flayed and the place of the skin is understood to
be the place sort of, you know, away from not where the
severing was made when it was flayed but where the sort of
back was made. Apparently that was cleaner. You know, when you pull
it away and whatever, so the, if you're, if you're like removing
skin from chicken let's say, you know, you cut it here and
you pull it away, so the place where you just do the
nice clean pull at the back, that was presumably the cleaner way.
So basically the run is the opposite side of where the cut
was made to do the flaying on the outside. Okay. ובית העור
מבחוץ. Uveit ha'or mibachutz.
What?
Okay.
השני בשתי ידיו, Hasheni bishtei yadav, the second guy, B there, had
the two front arms. של ימין בימינו ושל שמאל בשמאלו, Shel yamin
bimino veshel smol bismolo, the right in the right, the left in
the left. ובית העור מבחוץ, Uveit ha'or mibachutz, the, you place of
the skin was on the outside. The outside was facing out. השלישי
בעוקץ וברגל, Hashelishi be'oketz uveragel, the third guy had the rear, the
tail, and the left and the left leg. העוקץ בימינו, Ha'oketz bimino,
the rear was in his right hand. והאליה מדודלת בין אצבעותיו, Veha'alyah
medudelet bein etzbe'otav, and the fat tail was sort of suspended between
his fingers, that's presumably why it was in the right because the
fat tail was considered like the fat is always considered to be
the best part of the
korban. ואצבע הכבד ושתי כליות עמה, Ve'etzba hakaved ushtei klayot imah, and
the lobe of the liver and the two kidneys were with it.
הרגל של שמאל בשמאלו, Haregel shel smol bismolo, and the left leg
was in his left hand, there's also a nice left and left.
ובית העור מבחוץ, Uveit ha'or mibachutz, and the outer part was facing
outward. The skin part. הרביעי בחזה ובגרה, Harevi'i bachazeh uvagerah, the fourth
guy, D in our picture, he got the
chest and the throat area, which also had the, you know, the
lungs and the heart, etc. החזה בימינו, Hachazeh bimino, the chest in
the right. והגרה בשמאלו, Vehagerah bismolo, and the lungs and the throat
in the
left. וצלעותיו בין שתי אצבעותיו, Vetzla'otav bein shtei etzbe'otav, and its sort
of sides of the,
not the ribs but the sides, whatever, the flaps or whatever were
between his fingers of the throat of the throat of the...
No, he wasn't the guy that had the... Oh, you're right, but
it means the two little, I guess it means those two little
צלעות, tzela'ot, right? Okay. Okay. Does the chest...
What about all these ribs, right? Yeah, so they're going up also,
right?
Yeah, everything's going up.
Okay, so that's the chest, he gets the ribs?
Well, the stuff right under his space, yeah, exactly, yeah.
The guy had a
flank, you know,
the mostly, but the front part of the ribs are here in
your chest, right. Okay. So yeah, Michael, you're right, because
it said what we did was you left the two little things
here, the two little here, so the two little the space between
the two little ribs at the bottom went with the rear flank,
with the rear that piece C, and the two little ribs here
at the top went with the chest area with the throat area
at the top, you're correct.
So that's what it means by the ribs, thank you.
Okay, good thing I had you here, Michael. All right now, החמישי
בשתי דפנות, Hachamishi bishtei defanot, the guy number five, E over there,
he had the two flanks. Those you imagine are big, again this
is a sheep, so maybe it's not so bad. של ימין בימינו
ושל שמאל בשמאלו, Shel yamin bimino veshel smol bismolo, the right in
the right, the left in the left. Again the left was the
one which was bigger because it had the spine but the right
was called the big one because it had the liver. ובית העור
מבחוץ. Uveit ha'or mibachutz. and the outside facing out. השישי, hashishi, the
sixth guy, בקרביים, bekirvayim, he got the inner organs, הנתונים בבזך, hanitunim
babazeich, and they were put in some type of a vessel, הכרעיים
על גביהן, hachera'ayim al gabeihen, and I was waiting for Michael to
ask, he cut off the feed at the beginning, who brought up
the feet? So here it tells you, the feet went with the
inner organs. That you can understand, that was like, those were seen
as like the real dirty parts, except for the feet. The feet,
inner organs, okay, מלמעלה milmala on top of them. Okay, phew, so
that was the dismemberment of the sheep.
To me it seems, what if this was a cow? Would they
have to do the same thing, just have to figure out...
More people, they needed more people.
No, I know, but would
they still hang it up by a leg and do everything...
exactly? Exactly, yeah. Just thought like it's a big cow.
I know, you gotta get a lot more people involved. Right.
Okay, would it be more people or just like a כהן kohen
had to have this massive, you know, chunk of...
No, there are definitely more people. It says מפורש meforash in the
משנה mishnah that there are more, I forget the exact number, but
there are more כהנים kohanim involved when it's a cow, you have
to definitely separate it out into more people. Yes.
Do they line up and wait until everybody is ready?
It sounds like it, yes, that's what it sounds like. Correct. Yes,
exactly. Exactly, exactly. Okay,
and again to read, Michael was correct, it does separate, here they
would clean the stomach and the whatever and the intestines, the inner
organs. The stomach would be in its own separate room, then the
intestines on those tables.
Now, השביעי בסולת, hashvi'i basolet, the seventh guy did the flour, השמיני
בחביתין, hashmini bachavitin, the eighth guy did, brought the חביתין, chavitin, which
was the מנחה mincha of the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, התשיעי ביין,
hatishi beyayin, the ninth person brought the wine. Interesting that they separate
out the wine and the סולת, solet, which are a unified קרבן,
korban, but presumably they're doing all of the flour stuff first and
then the wine. So they had nine people there. הלכו ונתנום
מחצי הכבש ולמטה, halchu unetnum mechatzu hakevesh ulemata, they went and they
placed them on the lower half of the ramp, because they're going
to also do this in two stages: first they bring it to
the lower half and from the lower half to the top. במערבו,
bema'aravo, in the west of the ramp, which is interesting because you
would normally travel up on the east. But I guess maybe that's
the reason that the next procession, which is going to come soon
after, is going to go up on the east, so you want
to be over to the west and get access to...
Why can't... I thought... I would have thought that one guy would
just go up the ramp...
why do they do it in two stages? Yeah. They do a
lot of this stuff in two stages. To me it seems just
as a way of making things more involved. Yeah. More involved and
more, you know, right, there's just more busyness around it. It's more
of a sense of like it's a big deal. It happens in
stages. Okay, did they put it on the western side because it's
שכינה במערב, shechina bama'arav, is that why?
No,
I think they just put it on the western side because they're
traveling up the east. So you put it down on the west
so the next procession, procession goes up on the east and has
access to it.
Okay.
Yeah, let me check the מפרש. mefareish.
Yeah, basically that's what he says. It's just to make it that
they can keep on walking up on the east, so they walk
up on the east, they put it down on the west, and
then the next and they have the they still have the open
lane, and then when they come up next, then they'll get it
from the west there and they'll keep on moving it up.
Oh, yeah, yeah, but this note says something interesting about other things,
that the west of the ramp was closer to the היכל, heichal,
was the other way.
All right, anyway, so they went up here, they went up so
now they've got it dismembered, it's actually here. Right, so here's where
the dismemberment is. They've got this procession, they all walk they walk
up the east of the ramp, they get to somewhere right before
the midpoint, and they put all of this stuff down somewhere here,
okay, on the west side. So they're leaving a free a free
pathway, and then they're going to come up later and pick it
up from there and bring it to the top. All right.
Okay. All
right, where are we? מחצי הכבש ולמטה במערבו. mechatzu hakevesh ulemata bema'aravo.
ומלחום, umelachum,
they put salt on them, even on the מנחות, menachot, because you
have to put salt on everything that goes on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Is this salt now on the on the ramp?
They are they they who had the salt? That's a good question.
ובאו להם ללשכת הגזית, uvau lahem lelishkat hagazit, and they came to
the לשכת הגזית, lishkat hagazit, which is the again the place, the
chamber of the hewn stone where the סנהדרין sanhedrin sat לקרוא את
שמע. likro et shema. Now they're actually going to daven. Actually what's
quite interesting and I think it's something that's important to pay attention
to is the relationship of תפילה tefillah and קרבנות. korbanot. So they,
you know, you have to say קריאת שמע, kriat shema, and you
say it early. It's remember it's just the morning star. There's this
idea, there's a whole question that קריאת שמע kriat shema ideally maybe
should be said even before sunrise. And
at as it starts to get very light, so maybe it's the
ideal time to say שמע, shema, that's one reason they're saying it
now. But there could be another reason: maybe you want to do
davening actually before, not just as a personal thing, "I want to
get my davening done before I do other stuff," but maybe
conceptually framing the קרבנות korbanot in the context of תפילה. tefillah. So
before you actually are מקריב makriv now you did, it is true,
בזריקת הדם. bizrikat hadam. You were זורק את הדם, zorek et hadam,
so technically the תמיד tamid has already been הוקרב hukrav technically. but
it hasn't been burned, and you know, that's ריח ניחוח rei'ach nihoach
and so on, and to have דאווענינג davening in front of that.
That's at least what the מפרשים meforshim say. If you look at
the מפרש meforsh here on the left-hand column, it says ליקוטי שמע,
Liqqutei Shema, ולאחר קריאת שמע יקטיר את הקטורת. v'le'achar qariat shema yaqtir
et haqetoret. He emphasizes that's the one thing that hasn't been done
yet because technically, as I said, the תמיד tamid has been brought,
but the קטורת qetoret hasn't been brought, the incense. והכי נכון הדבר
שיתפללו קודם שיקטיר שום הקטר vehachi nakhon hadavar sheyitpallelu qodem sheyaqtir shum
haqter because it's not only before the incense is burned, but it's
also before the fats and the limbs are burned, and that תפילה
tefillah should come before that, ויעל קרבנם לריח ניחוח. veya'al qorbanam l'rei'ach
nihoach. And the fact that you pray first means that the sacrifice
will now be accepted because although technically it was effective when you
threw the דם, dam, the idea that it is accepted out of
desire and the raising of the smoke and the ריח ניחוח, rei'ach
nihoach, right, that's the very central part of this, and that should
be framed by the תפילה. tefillah. So there's something very beautiful about
that idea and it goes to the really heart of the question
about the relationship of תפילה tefillah to קרבנות. qorbanot. Okay.
Did they have any sort of שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei or they
just said שמע Shema only?
We will see that as we continue. So hold off on that.
And they were wearing תפילין tefillin as well? They were wearing it
already.
Were
they—yeah, I think we're gonna get to that.
And were those לויים Levi'im doing like שירה shirah and—all right, I
go—you gotta hold off on all this. Anyway, so the לשכת הגזית
Lishkat Hagazit was here, it was right by, I mean, in fact,
it was where the, it was right by the opening to the
עזרה.
azarah. So they did this and then they came to the northwest
of the לשכת הגזית Lishkat Hagazit
and now they're going to say שמע. Shema. Let's just read a
little גמרא. Gemara. Okay. ורמיא גבי רגל כעקידת יצחק בן אברהם. u'ramya
gabei regel ka'aqeidat Yitzhaq ben Avraham. So they did an עקידה, aqeidah,
foot and leg, like יצחק בן אברהם. Yitzhaq ben Avraham. Now, number
one is, did they really do this by אברהם Avraham like this?
Is that how you imagine it? None of the pictures had it
that way. All of the pictures, I mean the contemporaneous pictures. But
that's a little bit strange. The other thing interesting is עקידת יצחק
בן אברהם Aqeidat Yitzhaq ben Avraham and if you remember from זבחים
Zevahim and מנחות, Menahot, we did learn some things from the עקידה,
aqeidah, like that you need a מאכלת, ma'akhelet, knife, we learned that
you needed a כלי שרת kli sharet for, you know, you need
a כלי kli for the שחיטה. shehitah.
So it is, you know, that's very important too, the way in
which the עקידה aqeidah serves as a model for קרבנות. qorbanot. You
know, the whole idea is what's your whole idea of the עקידה?
aqeidah? Is it like God was saying I never want this and
therefore the whole thing actually shouldn't be used as a model? But
okay, but at the same time, you know, he was, you know,
it was what he was at least about to do. And to
what degree does that mean, you know, I mean sometimes in some
of our liturgy, we emphasize the עקידה aqeidah as if it took
place and it should be seen as a קרבן qorban and you
know, so that idea to me it's a, there's a lot more
to unpack there about using the whole idea of the עקידת יצחק
Aqeidat Yitzhaq for the model for קרבנות. qorbanot.
Did you say there was no גמרא Gemara when we first started?
There's no גמרא Gemara in מידות. Middot. There's a גמרא Gemara in
תמיד. Tamid. Oh, there's a... very little, but there is. Okay, like
yesterday was all משנה Mishnah and coming up it's gonna be like
a lot of משנה Mishnah with no גמרא. Gemara. Okay. לא היו
כופתין את הטלה, Lo hayu koftin et hataleh, they would not bind
it. Now, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why? Now, it could have just
said because we want it to be like עקידת יצחק בן אברהם.
Aqeidat Yitzhaq ben Avraham. But interestingly it doesn't say that. It says
the reason they didn't bind it, whatever this means, all four together
or two in front, two in back, what's the reason? רב הונא
ורב חסדא, Rav Huna v'Rav Hisda, חד אמר משום ביזוי קדשים, had
amar mishum bizui qodashim, it's disgraceful. Somehow that's seen as, not exactly
clear why that's seen as disgraceful. It could be that that's right,
it could be that that's the way you would do it normally,
that when you would normally have to carry a sheep or move,
take them to the butcher, that's the normal way you would do
it. וחד אמר, v'had amar, the other says, משום דמהלכו בחוקי העמים,
mishum d'mahalkhu behuqqei ha'amim, that's the way the non-Jews do it in
their sacrifices and we want to be different. It's even butchering it?
No, no, I assume sacrifices.
Now,
again, it's interesting it doesn't say the reason for עקידת יצחק בן
אברהם, Aqeidat Yitzhaq ben Avraham, which is interesting, which means that maybe
that's not such—maybe that was more descriptive. That's not really what makes
us do it that way and what makes us do it that
way is to avoid doing it this way. מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu,
what difference does it make what reason you give? איכא בינייהו דכפתי'
בשיראי. ika beinaihu d'kaftei b'shiraei. Let's say you bound it with silk
scarves, או בשושלתא דדהבא, o b'shushalta d'dahava, or with some type of
gold strap. So you can't claim it's a ביזיון, bizayon, I mean
you're doing it with silk and with gold, but it still would
be חוקי הגויים, huqqei hagoyim, it's still would be the way the
non-Jews bring their sacrifices and we want to bind it in a
different way. תנן התם, Tnan hatam, we taught over there, שלוש עשרה
שולחנות היו במקדש, shloshah asar shulhanot hayu baMiqdash, there were 13 שולחנות
shulhanot in the מקדש. Miqdash. Eight of—well, we're going to include—well, wait
one minute. שמונה של שיש, shemonah shel shayish, eight of marble, בבית
המטבחיים, b'veit hamitbehayim, in the place of the slaughtering, שעליהם מדיחין את
הקרביים, she'aleihem madihin et haqirbayim, that's where you would rinse out the
intestines. שנים במערבה של כבש, shnayim b'ma'aravah shel kevesh, two at the
west of the ramp, אחד של שיש ואחד של כסף, ehad shel
shayish v'ehad shel kesef, one of marble, one of silver. על של
שיש נותנים את האיברים, al shel shayish notnim et ha'eivarim, on the
marble one you would put the limbs. Now, of course, what do
you mean put the limbs? We have them carrying it, but maybe
it would mean by other קרבנות, qorbanot, not the תמיד. tamid. Okay?
So you שחט shahat it, you dismember it, maybe, you know, based
on the rotations that they have and who's bringing it up, so
that would be a resting place to put some of the limbs.
Exactly. The גמרא Gemara is going to say that. You see you
have your picture right over there. ועל של כסף כלי שרת, ve'al
shel kesef klei sharet, and the silver one you would put your
various holy vessels. So those would be places of just, you know,
things to place things down on while you're moving on to other
things for the time being. ובאולם, Uve'ulam, and in the אולם, Ulam,
right, which is the space here right before the היכל, Heichal, this
space, okay, the whatever, the ante-chamber or the... what do we call
the אולם? Ulam? Hall we call it now? But anyway, sometimes anyway,
שנים מבפנים, shnayim mibifnim, there would be two on the inside of
that אולם Ulam space, that hall before the היכל. Heichal. על פתח
הבית, al petach habayit, right by the opening, right by the opening
to the actual היכל. Heichal. אחד של כסף ואחד של זהב, echad
shel kesef ve'echad shel zahav, one of gold, one of silver. One
of silver, one of gold. על של כסף נותנים לחם הפנים, al
shel kesef notnim lechem hapanim, on the silver one you would put
the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim בכניסתו, bechnisato, when you were bringing it
in. So again you had to put it down, you had to
rest. They baked the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim somewhere here, they brought
it in here, and they put it down here again to do
things in two stages, to rest, and so on. ואחד של זהב,
ve'echad shel zahav, that's on the way in to bring the new
לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. ועל של זהב ביציאתו, ve'al shel zahav biyziato,
the gold one you would put the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim that
you took from inside the היכל Heichal on the way out, and
you would put it down there also to rest. Now why did
they have one of silver, one of gold? שמעלין בקודש ולא מורידין,
shema'alin bakodesh velo moridin, because you go up in holiness, not down.
And what... and when it's going on the table, the table where
the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim is, is what material? This is gold.
Gold. So you start on silver so that you can go up
from silver to gold. And then once it's on gold, you can't
go down. They didn't have platinum.
So then the next table it goes on also has to be
gold. So now we have twelve. Right? Eight for washing, two for
putting things down on by the ramp, two for the לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim in the אולם, Ulam, that's twelve.
There's a thirteenth here. It says השולחן של שיש, hashulchan shel shayish,
because the use just has the שולחן של שיש... shulchan shel shayish...
Yeah, that's weird. That's weird.
Go on. ואחד של זהב מבפנים, ve'echad shel zahav mibifnim, and of
course the thirteenth is, duh, is the שולחן shulchan where they actually
put the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. Okay? שעליו לחם הפנים תמיד, she'alav
lechem hapanim tamid, that's where the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim is. And
now let's just read what the גמרא'ס Gemara's comment on this and
we'll end with that for today. מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look,
אין עניות במקום עשירות, ein aniyut bimkom ashirut, there isn't poverty in
a place of wealth. אמאי עבדי דשיש, amai avdi deshayish, why did
you make the table, some of the tables out of marble? נעבדי
דכסף, na'avdi dechesef, make it out of silver. נעבדי דזהב, na'avdi dezahav,
make it out of gold. That's what Michael said. אמר רבי חנינא
בשם רבי אסי רבי אסי בשם רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק, amar
Rabbi Chanina beshem Rabbi Assi, Rabbi Assi beshem Rabbi Shmuel bar Rav
Yitzchak, מפני שהוא מרתיח, mipnei shehu martiach, because metals are... literally boil,
conduct heat, and will make the stuff warmer and will make it
spoil, and the marble is cold. So any place that you put
the intestines and the limbs were marble. So the marble one was
here where they slaughtered and here on the side of the altar
and places where you only put vessels or bread, that could have
been of silver and of gold as was appropriate. We'll pick up
tomorrow.